Ashraful Islam

aislam@uab.edu (929) 421-8226 Birmingham, AL, USA github.com/ashraful-islam-rafi linkedin.com/in/ashraful-islam-rafi Java, Python, C, C++, Racket, PHP, JavaScript

Summary

Computer Science graduate student at the University of Alabama at Birmingham (UAB) with over 2 years of academic research experience and over 7 years of industry experience taking on roles such as Software Engineer, and Programmer.

Education

University of Alabama at Birmingham | Alabama, USA

Jan 2022 - Dec 2024

• M.S. in Computer Science

Leading University | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Aug 2009 - Aug 2013

• B.Sc. In Computer Science & Engineering

Experience

Graduate Research Assistant | UAB | Alabama, USA

Jan 2022 - Present

- Brouhaha (Prototype Research Compiler): Leading a team of three students in developing Brouhaha, which currently outperforms other compilers like Chicken and Guile, achieving 3x better running times for certain benchmarks. This performance primarily results from performing control flow analysis (k-CFA) to detect function inlining opportunities.
- Compiler: Wrote a functional compiler in Racket that translates minimal Racket code into C++.

Software Engineer | BANGLA SEARCH ENGINE (PIPILIKA) | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Aug 2017 - Mar 2021

- Search Relevancy Improvement: Enhanced keyword-based search relevancy by redesigning the Apache Solr schema, extracting Bangla Unicode data, and implementing Solr's dismax query parser, gaining a 35% increase in search relevance.
- Large-Scale Data Search Portal: Developed a generic approach using **Scrapy** to crawl, parse, and index unstructured data from over 40,000 websites, boosting indexed data by 18% and enhancing search capabilities.
- Solr Analytic Library: Used **Spring Boot** to provide domain-specific time series data for Solr projects, improving reporting capabilities and reducing the debugging time by 20%.

Programmer | SOUTHEAST UNIVERSITY | Dhaka, Bangladesh

Apr 2015 - Aug 2017

- Served over 3 months as the in-charge of the Information Technology (IT) department, managing all IT operations and ensuring efficient and effective technology solutions across the organization.
- Introduced an Online Admission System using PHP, MySQL, and Bootstrap3, contributing to 25% of total admissions.
- Improved the University Support System software report generation time by 30% by redesigning the MySQL schema.
- Coordinated and monitored vendor company in developing Human Resources Management System (HRMS) software.

Software Developer | IT LAB SOLUTIONS LTD | Sylhet, Bangladesh

Sep 2013 - Dec 2014

Designed and developed customized web-based Shop Management software for over 5 different businesses.

Skills

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, C, C++, PHP, Racket, JavaScript.
- Databases/Frameworks/Technologies: Spring Boot, Servlet, Codeigniter, Jsoup, Scrapy, Bootstrap3, AJAX, MySQL, MongoDB, Apache Solr, HTML5, CSS3, Git, Docker, AWS, Maven, WordPress, SDLC, STLC, MVC, Agile, Scrum.

Extracurricular / Activities

- Judge: Served as a judge of the Summer 2023 Undergraduate Research Expo, UAB.
- Treasurer: Managed financial operations of the Bangladesh Student Association, a graduate student organization at UAB.
- Tutor: Conducted over 15 programming workshops focused on Data Structures and Algorithms at Leading University, with each session attended by more than 40 students.